<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>XML Patterns for Representing Critical Edition Data</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Developed by</resp>
               <name>Samuel J. Huskey</name>
               <name>Hugh Cayless</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Working guidelines for the Digital Latin Library</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital, with references to the Epidoc Guidelines</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div xml:id="LDLT-edition-structure">
            <head>Structure of an LDLT Edition</head>
            <p>This section describes the basic structure of the file that contains an edition for
               the Digital Latin Library's <bibl><title>Library of Digital Latin
                  Texts</title></bibl> (LDLT). The structure of an LDLT edition resembles the
               structure of a traditional printed critical edition:</p>
            <list>
               <head>Parts of an LDLT Edition</head>
               <item>Publication Details</item>
               <item>Front Matter</item>
               <item>Critical Text (including apparatus)</item>
               <item>Indices</item>
            </list>
            <p>Since every text is unique, not every LDLT edition will have all of these sections.
               The nature of the text and the editor's judgment will determine the contents of an
               edition. The purpose of this section is to define the parts of an LDLT edition and
               provide guidelines for representing them in XML.</p>
            <p>These guidelines are based on the standard set by the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI),
               with modification and customization to accommodate the special characteristics of
               Latin texts.</p>
            <div xml:id="general-structure">
               <p>The following is an example of the general overall structure of an XML file for an
                  LDLT edition:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <teiHeader>
                     <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                           <title>Bucolica</title>
                           <author>Calpurnius Siculus</author>
                           <editor>Jane Doe</editor>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                           <edition>First Edition</edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                           <publisher>Society for Classical Studies</publisher>
                           <distributor>Digital Latin Library</distributor>
                           <date>2016</date>
                           <availability>
                              <license target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"
                                 >Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                 License.</license>
                           </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <seriesStmt>
                           <title level="s">Library of Digital Latin Texts</title>
                           <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
                        </seriesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                           <p>Born digital.</p>
                        </sourceDesc>
                     </fileDesc>
                  </teiHeader>
                  <text>
                     <front xml:id="front">
                        <div xml:id="preface">
                           <head>Preface</head>
                           <p>General introductory remarks about the edition.</p>
                           <div xml:id="preface-section-1">
                              <!--This is a subsection within the preface. Editors should use
                              subsections to organize the content of the edition's preface.-->
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div xml:id="bibliography">
                           <head>Bibliography</head>
                           <!--This is where the bibliography for the edition is listed.-->
                           <div xml:id="bibliography-manuscripts">
                              <head>Manuscripts</head>
                              <!--Descriptions of manuscripts, using <gi>listWit</gi>.-->
                           </div>
                           <div xml:id="bibliography-early-editions">
                              <head>Early Editions</head>
                              <!--Bibliographical details for early editions or editiones vetustiores, using
                                 <gi>listBibl</gi> with <att>type</att>="editions-witnesses".-->
                           </div>
                           <div xml:id="bibliography-modern-editions">
                              <head>Modern Editions</head>
                              <!--Bibliographical details for modern editions and commentaries, using
                                 <gi>listBibl</gi> with <att>type</att>="editions-sources".-->
                           </div>
                           <div xml:id="bibliography-secondary-sources">
                              <head>Secondary Sources</head>
                              <!--Bibliographical details for articles, notes, books, and other sources,
                              using <gi>listBibl</gi> with <att>type</att>="secondary-sources".-->
                           </div>
                           <div xml:id="bibliography-scholars">
                              <head>List of Scholars Referred to By Name</head>
                              <!-- A list of the names of individual scholars referred to by name in the 
                                 apparatus, if they are not listed elsewhere in the bibliography (e.g., 
                                 as the editor of an edition or author of an article). -->
                           </div>
                        </div>
                        <div xml:id="conspectus">
                           <head>Conspectus</head>
                           <!--A key to the special sigla and abbreviations used in the edition (drawn
                           from the <att>xml:id</att>'s assigned to the various items in the
                           bibliography).-->
                        </div>
                     </front>
                     <body>
                        <div type="edition" xml:id="edition-text" xml:space="preserve">
                        <div type="textpart" n="1" xml:id="part1">
                           <head>Title of First Part</head>
                           <!--Text goes here, according to the conventions laid out elsewhere in these guidelines.-->
                        </div>
                        <div type="textpart" n="2" xml:id="part2">
                           <head>Title of Second Part</head>
                           <!--Each new major section (e.g., book, volume) goes in a new <gi>div</gi>.-->
                        </div>
                     </div>
                     </body>
                     <back>
                        <!--The content of the back matter will be determined in consultation between
                        the editor and the staff of the DLL. Because LDLT editions are encoded, the
                        matter traditionally found in the back of a printed critical edition may be
                        generated by applications instead of having to be entered manually.
                        Nevertheless, there is space here for notes, indices, and other kinds of
                        information.-->
                     </back>
                  </text>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="publication-details">
               <head>Publication Details</head>
               <p>A traditional critical edition in print has a title page announcing the title of
                  the work, its author, the editor(s), and details of publication. In an LDLT
                  edition, these details are presented as structured data within a TEI header
                     (<gi>teiHeader</gi>). For example:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <teiHeader>
                     <fileDesc>
                        <titleStmt>
                           <title>Bucolica</title>
                           <author>Calpurnius Siculus</author>
                           <editor>Jane Doe</editor>
                        </titleStmt>
                        <editionStmt>
                           <edition>First Edition</edition>
                        </editionStmt>
                        <publicationStmt>
                           <publisher>Society for Classical Studies</publisher>
                           <distributor>Digital Latin Library</distributor>
                           <date>2016</date>
                           <availability>
                              <license target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"
                                 >Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
                                 License.</license>
                           </availability>
                        </publicationStmt>
                        <seriesStmt>
                           <title level="s">Library of Digital Latin Texts</title>
                           <biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope>
                        </seriesStmt>
                        <sourceDesc>
                           <p>Born digital.</p>
                        </sourceDesc>
                     </fileDesc>
                  </teiHeader>
               </egXML>
               <p>Since a critical edition is often based upon many sources (e.g., manuscripts,
                  previous editions, commentaries, etc.), the <gi>teiHeader</gi> for an LDLT edition
                  does not hew strictly to the TEI guidelines for <gi>sourceDesc</gi>. The sources
                  for an LDLT edition are documented and described in the edition's front
                  matter.</p>
               <p>Just as an editor is not expected to create the title page and document the
                  publication information, this section of an LDLT is the responsibility of the DLL
                  staff.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="front-matter">
               <head>Front Matter</head>
               <p>The <gi>front</gi> contains numbered divisions and subdivisions (e.g.,
                     <gi>div1</gi>, <gi>div2</gi>) corresponding to the preface, bibliography, and
                  conspectus for the edition.</p>
               <p>The <hi rend="bold">preface</hi> lays out (in prose, using <gi>p</gi>) the
                  argument for the edition. It also describes the textual tradition and the major
                  sources for it, which is why it is recommended to compile the bibliography first,
                  to take advantage of the ability to link to individual entries in the
                  bibliography. For example, prefaces traditionally contain a description in prose
                  of the manuscripts consulted in establishing the text of the edition. The preface
                  of an LDLT can include prose descriptions of manuscripts, but it should also link
                  to structured (i.e., machine-readable) data for the manuscript in the edition's
                  bibliography.</p>
               <p>The elements available in all TEI documents are available for use in the preface.
                  For example, an editor might want to make a table comparing the readings of
                  manuscript families. In that case, the editor would use <gi>table</gi> and its
                  related elements.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="bibliography">
               <head>Bibliography</head>
               <!-- Issue: Should a consensus siglum be an xml:id on a <listBibl> containing the items, or a separate siglum listed elsewhere? -->
               <!-- Issue: One <forename> for first and middle names? Or separate <forename> for each? -->
               <!-- Issue: Nicknames. Should they be in parentheses with <surname>, or should they be in <addname> by themselves? -->
               <p>The bibliography presents opportunities for leveraging the digital nature of an
                  LDLT edition. Because every item in the bibliography is encoded as structured data
                  (contained in <gi>msDesc</gi> or <gi>biblStruct</gi>), the bibliography itself can
                  become a useful tool for finding and using resources, especially those that are
                  available online.</p>
               <p>The bibliography is all the more useful as a tool if it is created and made
                  available via <ref target="http://www.zotero.org">Zotero</ref>, an open, online
                  resource for building and managing bibliographies. In addition to providing an
                  interface for compiling and managing a bibliography, Zotero can also export
                  bibliographies in a TEI XML format that requires little to no modification for
                  inclusion in an LDLT edition. Users can copy and paste Zotero information directly
                  into an LDLT edition file. For these reasons, it is highly recommended that all
                  LDLT editions have a corresponding Zotero repository for their bibliography.</p>
               <p>Unfortunately, Zotero does not currently provide a format for describing and
                  cataloging manuscripts, so that information must be entered manually. For that
                  reason, and for the sake of completeness, the following sections provide
                  information for encoding items in the bibliography, with examples.</p>
               <div xml:id="bibliography-structure">
                  <head>Structure of the Bibliography</head>
                  <p>The bibliography should be organized according to the following structure:</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Structure of the Bibliography for an LDLT Edition</head>
                     <item>Manuscripts (<att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-manuscripts")</item>
                     <item>Editions<list>
                           <item>Early Editions
                              (<att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-editions-witnesses"</item>
                           <item>Modern Editions
                              (<att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-editions-sources")</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Secondary Sources
                        (<att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-secondary-sources")</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Additionally, there should be a list of the names of individual scholars
                        (<att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-scholars") referred to by name in the
                     apparatus, if they are not listed elsewhere in the bibliography (e.g., as the
                     editor of an edition or author of an article). It is common, for example, to
                     refer to a scholar whose unpublished notes appear in a commentary or who has
                     corresponded with the editor. For ease of reference, these sources should be
                     listed with information about where the information can be verified.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="bibliography-sigla">
                  <head>Human- and Machine-Readable Sigla, Symbols, and Abbreviations</head>
                  <p>Printed editions have long used a system of shorthand references for
                     manuscripts and other materials in the bibliography. Single letters, or <emph
                        rend="italic">sigla</emph>, stand for a manuscript, and the last name of a
                     scholar serves as a shorthand reference to an edition, commentary, or other
                     work of scholarship. Centuries of publication have demontrated that sigla and
                     other symbols and abbreviations are efficient, effective, and economic ways of
                     conveying complex information in critical editions. But they are also examples
                     of visually encoded information that is available only to human readers. In
                     other words, a human might see <hi rend="bold">N²</hi> and correctly interpret
                     it within a perticular edition as meaning "text written by the second person in
                     a succession of people who wrote in the manuscript known as codex Neapolitanus
                     V A 8." But a machine will interpret the same information as simply the letter
                     N with a superscript numeral 2 next to it.</p>
                  <p>To make an LDLT text readable by both humans and machines, there must be a
                     system of reference that leverages both the traditional approach that has
                     served textual criticism so well for so long and new ways of making information
                     available to machines for processing and sophisticated analysis. To accomplish
                     that goal, each item in the bibliography of an LDLT edition must have two
                     unique identifiers: one for humans and one for machines.</p>
                  <p>For the latter, the XML specification has the <att>xml:id</att> attribute,
                     which has <ref target="https://www.w3.org/TR/xml-id/">strict rules</ref> that
                     do not allow for the traditional conventions used in critical editions. For the
                     former, the TEI standard has <att>n</att>, which allows for all of the usual
                     conventions. In same instances, the two attributes might be identical. For
                     example, if a manuscript is known by the siglum <hi rend="bold">V</hi>, it is
                     possible to identify it to machines as <att>xml:id</att>="V" and to humans as
                        <att>n</att>="V". But if an editor must refer to a number of manuscripts
                     from the same collection designated as <hi rend="bold">V</hi>, the usual
                     practice in a printed critical edition is to use the letter V to stand for the
                     collection with subscript numerals distinguishing the different manuscripts. In
                     an LDLT edition, the second one in the series would have <att>xml:id</att> of
                     "V2", but the <att>n</att> would be V₂. Humans can read and understand both
                     easily, but machines need a simpler method of identifying something.</p>
                  <p><hi rend="bold">Every entry, regardless of type, in the bibliography of an LDLT
                        edition must have values for both <att>xml:id</att> and <att>n</att>.</hi>
                     Otherwise, the edition will not be able to make full use of the digital format.
                     Morever, if an entry lacks <att>n</att>, it will not be available for the print
                     version of the edition.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="bibliography-ms-description">
                  <head>Manuscripts</head>
                  <p>Manuscript description is a discipline unto itself, with an entire module in
                     the TEI guidelines devoted to it (<ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/MS.html">10
                        Manuscript Description</ref>). Since fully describing every manuscript
                     consulted for an edition could be prohibitive, these guidelines set forth the
                     minimum required for the LDLT.</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="listWit"/>
                        <specDesc key="witness"/>
                        <specDesc key="msDesc"/>
                        <specDesc key="msIdentifier"/>
                        <specDesc key="settlement"/>
                        <specDesc key="institution"/>
                        <specDesc key="repository"/>
                        <specDesc key="idno"/>
                        <specDesc key="altIdentifier"/>
                        <specDesc key="physDesc"/>
                        <specDesc key="objectDesc"/>
                        <specDesc key="supportDesc"/>
                        <specDesc key="handDesc"/>
                        <specDesc key="handNote"/>
                        <specDesc key="history"/>
                        <specDesc key="origin"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>listWit</gi> (list of witnesses) contains the descriptions of manuscript
                     sources for the edition.</p>
                  <p><gi>witness</gi> (witness) groups the information about a manuscript, including
                     the name used to refer to the manuscript in the edition (e.g., Codex
                     Neapolitanus V A 8). Its <att>xml:id</att> is the unique machine-readable
                     identifier to be used when referring to the manuscript's data (e.g., in the
                        <att>wit</att> of a <gi>rdg</gi> in the apparatus criticus).</p>
                  <p><gi>msDesc</gi> (manuscript description) groups the elements that compose the
                     description of the manuscript:</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>Required Elements in the Manuscript Description</head>
                     <item><gi>msIdentifier</gi> (manuscript identifier) groups information about
                        the location and inventory number of the manuscript.</item>
                     <item><gi>settlement</gi> contains the name of the place (e.g., city) where the
                        manuscript is located.</item>
                     <item><gi>institution</gi> contains the name of the library that houses the
                        manuscript</item>
                     <item><gi>repository</gi> contains the name of the collection to which the
                        manuscript belongs.</item>
                     <item><gi>idno</gi> (identifier) contains the catalog or inventory information
                        for the manuscript.</item>
                     <item><gi>altIdentifier</gi> (alternative identifier) contains other
                        information (i.e., in addition to the <gi>idno</gi>) used to identify the
                        manuscript.</item>
                     <item><gi>phsyDesc</gi> (physical description) groups information about the
                        manuscript.</item>
                     <item><gi>objectDesc</gi> (object description) contains <gi>supportDesc</gi>
                        (support description). It may have <att>form</att> to identify whether the
                        manuscript is a codex, a set of unbound leaves, or other form.</item>
                     <item><gi>supportDesc</gi> (support description) is a self-closing element that
                        identifies (in <att>material</att>) the material upon which the manuscript's
                        text is written (e.g., "parchment").</item>
                     <item><gi>handDesc</gi> (hand description) groups information about the
                        distinct hands that wrote in the manuscript. Use <att>hands</att> with the
                        value of the number of hands detectable in the manuscript.</item>
                     <item><gi>handNote</gi> is a self-closing element with attributes to
                        distinguish one hand from another. Each <gi>handNote</gi> has an
                           <att>xml:id</att> with a unique identifier (based on the
                           <att>xml:id</att> of the manuscript), an <att>n</att> with a
                        human-readable version of the value of the hand's <att>xml:id</att>,
                           <att>scope</att> with value "major" or "minor" to indicate the extent of
                        the hand's contribution, and, if necessary, <att>corresp</att> with the
                        value of the <att>xml:id</att> for any discussion of the hand's contribution
                        in the preface or elsewhere in the addition. Note that the first hand should
                        also have <att>sameAs</att> with the value of the manuscript's
                           <att>xml:id</att>, so that references to both <hi rend="bold">N</hi> and
                           <hi rend="bold">N¹</hi> will point to the same entity, that is, the
                        original copyist.</item>
                     <item><gi>history</gi> groups information about the date of the
                        manuscript.</item>
                     <item><gi>origin</gi> encloses <gi>origDate</gi>, which contains the Roman
                        numeral for the century in which the manuscript was written, or the Arabic
                        numeral for the year, if known. If century is used, include
                           <att>notBefore</att> and <att>notAfter</att> with appropriate values. If
                        year is used, enclose it with <gi>date</gi>.</item>
                  </list>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <listWit>
                        <head>First family</head>
                        <witness xml:id="N" n="N">Codex Neapolitanus V A 8 <msDesc>
                              <msIdentifier>
                                 <settlement>Naples</settlement>
                                 <repository>Biblioteca Nazionale di Napoli</repository>
                                 <idno>V A 8</idno>
                                 <altIdentifier>
                                    <idno>380</idno>
                                 </altIdentifier>
                              </msIdentifier>
                              <physDesc>
                                 <objectDesc form="codex">
                                    <supportDesc material="parch"/>
                                 </objectDesc>
                                 <handDesc hands="3">
                                    <handNote xml:id="N1" n="N¹" sameAs="#N" scope="major"
                                       corresp="#Ndesc-manusprima"/>
                                    <handNote xml:id="N2" n="N²" scope="major"
                                       corresp="#Ndesc-manusaltera"/>
                                    <handNote xml:id="N3" n="N³" scope="minor"
                                       corresp="#Ndesc-manustertia"/>
                                 </handDesc>
                              </physDesc>
                              <history>
                                 <origin>
                                    <origDate notAfter="1500" notBefore="1400">XV</origDate>
                                 </origin>
                              </history>
                           </msDesc>
                        </witness>
                        <witness xml:id="G" n="G">Codex Gaddianus pl. 90, 12 inf. <msDesc>
                              <msIdentifier>
                                 <settlement>Florence</settlement>
                                 <repository>Biblioteca Medicea Laurenziana</repository>
                                 <idno>plut. 90, 12 inf.</idno>
                              </msIdentifier>
                              <physDesc>
                                 <objectDesc form="codex">
                                    <supportDesc material="paper"/>
                                 </objectDesc>
                                 <handDesc hands="2">
                                    <handNote xml:id="G1" n="G¹" sameAs="#G"/>
                                    <handNote xml:id="G2" n="G²"/>
                                 </handDesc>
                              </physDesc>
                              <history>
                                 <origin>
                                    <origDate notAfter="1500" notBefore="1400" xml:id="witGdate"
                                       >XV</origDate>
                                    <note target="#witGdate">saec. XV ineunte scriptus</note>
                                 </origin>
                              </history>
                           </msDesc>
                        </witness>
                     </listWit>
                  </egXML>
                  <p>Note that <gi>note</gi> may be used to specify the portion of the century in
                     which a manuscript was written, if known.</p>
                  <p>If it is important to distinguish among families of manuscripts, separate
                        <gi>listWit</gi> containers (each with an identifying <gi>head</gi>) should
                     be used. In cases of multiple <gi>listWit</gi> containers, each
                        <gi>listWit</gi> should have a unique <att>xml:id</att> to use when
                     referring to the family itself or a consensus of readings in that family.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="bibliography-sources">
                  <head>Other Sources</head>
                  <div xml:id="bibliography-common-elements">
                     <head>Common Elements for All Entries</head>
                     <p>All entries, regardless of the type, will have certain common elements.</p>
                     <div xml:id="bibliography-biblStruct">
                        <head><gi>biblStruct</gi></head>
                        <p>Entries for items other than manuscripts should be contained in
                              <gi>biblStruct</gi> with <att>xml:id</att> and <att>n</att> as <ref
                              target="#bibliography-sigla">described above</ref>. Entries should
                           also be classified with <att>type</att> and encoded according to the
                           guidelines and examples below.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div xml:id="bibliography-pub">
                        <head>Publication Information</head>
                        <p>Publication information for all types of entries should be handled with
                           these elements:</p>
                        <p><specList>
                              <specDesc key="imprint"/>
                              <specDesc key="pubPlace"/>
                              <specDesc key="publisher"/>
                              <specDesc key="date"/>
                           </specList></p>
                        <p><gi>imprint</gi> groups information pertaining to the publication of the
                           edition</p>
                        <p><gi>pubPlace</gi> (place of publication) contains the name of the place
                           where the edition was published, as it appears on the title page (e.g.,
                           Lipsiae instead of Leipzig). If the place is unknown, <gi>pubPlace</gi>
                           should be self-closing (e.g., &lt;pubPlace/&gt;).</p>
                        <!-- Value if self-closing: "s.l." (sine loco) -->
                        <p><gi>publisher</gi> contains the name of the publisher, as it appears on
                           the title page. If the publisher's name is unknown, <gi>publisher</gi>
                           should be self-closing (e.g., &lt;publisher/&gt;).</p>
                        <!-- Value if self-closing: "s.n." (sine nomine) -->
                        <p><gi>date</gi> contains the date in Arabic numerals (e.g., 1504, not
                           MDIV). If the date is unknown, <gi>date</gi> should be self-closing
                           (e.g., &lt;date/&gt;).</p>
                        <!-- Value if self-closing: "s.d." (sine die). -->
                        <p><gi>note</gi> with <att>type</att>="url" contains the URL for an online
                           copy of the edition, if available.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:id="bibliography-editions">
                     <head>Editions</head>
                     <p>Previous editions must be classified in one of two categories: early
                        editions based on a single manuscript and modern critical editions based on
                        more than one source. This will have ramifications for how the editions are
                        handled in the apparatus criticus (see below, <ref
                           target="apparatus-criticus-patterns">Apparatus Criticus</ref>). This
                        distinction should be preserved in the bibliography with the use of two
                           <gi>listBibl</gi> lists, with <att>type</att> "witness" and "source",
                        respectively. The structure of the individual entries should be the same in
                        both lists.</p>
                     <p>The individual entries in each <gi>listBibl</gi> should have
                        <att>type</att>="book".</p>
                     <p>
                        <specList>
                           <specDesc key="biblStruct"/>
                           <specDesc key="monogr"/>
                           <specDesc key="title"/>
                           <specDesc key="editor"/>
                           <specDesc key="name"/>
                           <specDesc key="forename"/>
                           <specDesc key="surname"/>
                        </specList>
                     </p>
                     <p><gi>biblStruct</gi> (structured bibliographic citation) is the top-level
                        element for each edition. It should have <att>type</att> of "book". The
                        values for <att>xml:id</att> and <att>n</att> should be based on the surname
                        of the editor. Additionally, if the bibliography has been generated by
                        Zotero, each entry should have <att>corresp</att> with the URL for the entry
                        in the online Zotero bibliography.</p>
                     <p><gi>monogr</gi> (monographic level) contains bibliographic elements
                        describing an edition.</p>
                     <p><gi>title</gi> with <att>level</att>="m" (monographic) contains the full
                        title of the edition.</p>
                     <p><gi>editor</gi> contains information identifying the editor of the edition.
                        If the edition has more than one editor, use one <gi>editor</gi> for each
                        editor.</p>
                     <p><gi>name</gi> contains the value "Anonymous" in cases where the name of the
                        editor is not known.</p>
                     <p><gi>forename</gi> contains the first and middle names, or initials, of an
                        editor in cases where that information is known.</p>
                     <p><gi>surname</gi> contains the last name of an editor, in cases where that
                        information is known. If the editor is known by a nickname or a Latin name,
                        that information is enclosed in parentheses and quotation marks:
                        ("Ascensius").</p>
                     <p>Publication information is handled according to the guidelines in the <ref
                           target="#bibliography-pub">section above on publication</ref>.</p>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <biblStruct type="book" xml:id="Nordh." n="Nordh."
                           corresp="http://zotero.org/groups/542622/items/UAZU56E4">
                           <monogr>
                              <title level="m">[Bucolica]</title>
                              <editor>
                                 <name>Anonymous</name>
                              </editor>
                              <imprint>
                                 <pubPlace>Nordheim</pubPlace>
                                 <publisher/>
                                 <date/>
                              </imprint>
                           </monogr>
                        </biblStruct>
                        <biblStruct type="book" xml:id="s" n="s"
                           corresp="http://zotero.org/groups/542622/items/TXA4M9HA">
                           <monogr>
                              <title level="m">Buccolica, cum adnotatione Ascensiana, jam
                                 diligentius recognita</title>
                              <editor xml:id="Ascensius">
                                 <forename>Josse</forename>
                                 <surname>Badius ("Ascensius")</surname>
                              </editor>
                              <imprint>
                                 <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                                 <publisher>In vico Maturinorum a Durando Gerlerio</publisher>
                                 <date>1503</date>
                                 <note target="#s" type="url"
                                    >http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k841539v</note>
                              </imprint>
                           </monogr>
                        </biblStruct>
                     </egXML>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:id="books">
                     <head>Books Other than Editions</head>
                     <p>The bibliographical information for monographs, commentaries, and other
                        books that are not editions should be handled using these elements and
                        attributes:</p>
                     <p>
                        <specList>
                           <specDesc key="biblStruct"/>
                           <specDesc key="monogr"/>
                           <specDesc key="title"/>
                           <specDesc key="author"/>
                           <specDesc key="name"/>
                           <specDesc key="forename"/>
                           <specDesc key="surname"/>
                        </specList>
                     </p>
                     <p><gi>biblStruct</gi> (structured bibliographic citation) is the top-level
                        element for each book. It should have <att>type</att> of "book". The values
                        for <att>xml:id</att> and <att>n</att> should be based on the surname of the
                        author. Additionally, if the bibliography has been generated by Zotero, each
                        entry should have <att>corresp</att> with the URL for the entry in the
                        online Zotero bibliography.</p>
                     <p><gi>monogr</gi> (monographic level) groups bibliographic elements describing
                        a book.</p>
                     <p><gi>title</gi> with <att>level</att>="m" (monographic) contains the full
                        title of the book.</p>
                     <p><gi>author</gi> contains information identifying the author of the book. If
                        the book has more than one author, use one <gi>author</gi> for each
                        author.</p>
                     <p><gi>name</gi> contains the value "Anonymous" in cases where the name of the
                        author is not known.</p>
                     <p><gi>forename</gi> contains the first and middle names (middle name
                        optional), or initials, of an author in cases where that information is
                        known.</p>
                     <p><gi>surname</gi> contains the last name of an author, in cases where that
                        information is known.</p>
                     <p>Publication information is handled according to the guidelines in the <ref
                           target="#bibliography-pub">section above on publication</ref>.</p>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <biblStruct type="book" xml:id="Wilamowitz" n="Wilamowitz"
                           corresp="http://zotero.org/groups/542622/items/S2QGZ9FN">
                           <monogr>
                              <title level="m">Coniectanea</title>
                              <author>
                                 <forename>Ulrich von</forename>
                                 <surname>Wilamowitz-Moellendorff</surname>
                              </author>
                              <imprint>
                                 <pubPlace>Göttingen</pubPlace>
                                 <publisher>Dieterich'sche Druckerei</publisher>
                                 <date>1884</date>
                                 <note type="url"
                                    >http://hdl.handle.net/2027/nnc2.ark:/13960/t8jd66k2f</note>
                              </imprint>
                           </monogr>
                        </biblStruct>
                     </egXML>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:id="bibliography-articles">
                     <head>Articles</head>
                     <p>Bibliographic details for articles published in journals should be encoded
                        using the following elements and attributes:</p>
                     <p>
                        <specList>
                           <specDesc key="biblStruct"/>
                           <specDesc key="analytic"/>
                           <specDesc key="title"/>
                           <specDesc key="author"/>
                           <specDesc key="forename"/>
                           <specDesc key="surname"/>
                           <specDesc key="monogr"/>
                           <specDesc key="imprint"/>
                           <specDesc key="date"/>
                           <specDesc key="note"/>
                        </specList>
                     </p>
                     <p><gi>biblStruct</gi> (structured bibliographic citation) is the top-level
                        element for each article. It should have <att>type</att> of "journalArticle"
                        (note case). The values for <att>xml:id</att> and <att>n</att> should be
                        based on the surname of the author. Additionally, if the bibliography has
                        been generated by Zotero, each entry should have <att>corresp</att> with the
                        URL for the entry in the online Zotero bibliography.</p>
                     <p><gi>analytic</gi> (analytic level) contains items relating to an article
                        published within a journal volume.</p>
                     <list>
                        <head>Items Contained By <gi>analytic</gi></head>
                        <item><gi>title</gi> with <att>level</att>="a" contains the title of the
                           article.</item>
                        <item><gi>author</gi> contains information identifying the author of the
                           book. If the book has more than one author, use one <gi>author</gi> for
                           each author.</item>
                        <item><gi>forename</gi> contains the first and middle names (middle name
                           optional), or initials, of an author in cases where that information is
                           known.</item>
                        <item><gi>surname</gi> contains the last name of an author, in cases where
                           that information is known.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p><gi>monogr</gi> (monographic level) groups bibliographic elements describing
                        the journal.</p>
                     <list>
                        <head>Items Contained by <gi>mongr</gi></head>
                        <item><gi>title</gi> with <att>level</att>="j" contains the title of the
                           journal.</item>
                        <item><gi>imprint</gi> groups several <gi>biblScope</gi> elements defining
                           publication information. All numbers should be Arabic numerals.</item>
                        <item><gi>biblScope</gi> (scope of bibliographic reference) is used with
                              <att>unit</att> to indicate details of publication: <list>
                              <item><att>unit</att>="volume" contains the volume number of the
                                 journal in which the article has been published</item>
                              <item><att>unit</att>="issue" contains the number of the issue within
                                 the volume</item>
                              <item><att>unit</att>="page" contains the inclusive pages where the
                                 article may be found</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item><gi>date</gi> contains the year of publication</item>
                        <item><gi>note</gi> with <att>type</att>="url" contains the URL where the
                           article may be read online, if available.</item>
                     </list>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <biblStruct type="journalArticle" xml:id="Postgate" n="Postgate"
                           corresp="http://zotero.org/groups/542622/items/T9VQVNDS">
                           <analytic>
                              <title level="a">Some Suggestions on Calpurnius Siculus</title>
                              <author>
                                 <forename>John Percival</forename>
                                 <surname>Postgate</surname>
                              </author>
                           </analytic>
                           <monogr>
                              <title level="j">The Classical Review</title>
                              <imprint>
                                 <biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
                                 <biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
                                 <biblScope unit="page">213-214</biblScope>
                                 <date>1901</date>
                                 <note type="accessed">2016-05-26T16:32:29Z</note>
                                 <note type="url">http://www.jstor.org/stable/694806</note>
                              </imprint>
                           </monogr>
                        </biblStruct>
                     </egXML>
                     <p>Note that a review of an edition or other work should be handled in the same
                        way as a journal article, with the exception of the <gi>title</gi> in
                           <gi>analytic</gi>, which should begin with the words "Review of" followed
                        by the title of the work being reviewed.</p>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <biblStruct type="journalArticle" xml:id="Mueller" n="L. Mueller"
                           corresp="http://zotero.org/groups/542622/items/WJIX5IQM">
                           <analytic>
                              <title level="a">Review of "Calpurnii et Nemesiani Bucolica recensuit
                                 Henricus Schenkl, Lipsiae, G. Freytag, Pragae, F. Tempsky,
                                 1885"</title>
                              <author>
                                 <forename>Lucian</forename>
                                 <surname>Müller</surname>
                              </author>
                           </analytic>
                           <monogr>
                              <title level="j">Berliner philologische Wochenschrift</title>
                              <imprint>
                                 <biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
                                 <biblScope unit="page">1065-1073</biblScope>
                                 <date>1885</date>
                                 <note type="url"
                                    >http://hdl.handle.net/2027/uiug.30112023962282</note>
                              </imprint>
                           </monogr>
                        </biblStruct>
                     </egXML>
                  </div>
                  <div xml:id="bibliography-list-of-scholars">
                     <head>List of Scholars</head>
                     <p>Occasionally it is necessary to refer to a scholar whose unpublished work
                        has been quoted or paraphrased elsewhere. For example, editors often cite
                        Nicolaas Heinsius' unpublished conjectures, found in books in his own
                        library. But "Heins." does not help a reader find more information. That is
                        why the bibliography of an LDLT edition includes a list of scholars
                        mentioned by name in the edition, with information about where to find their
                        remarks, if they are available.</p>
                     <p>
                        <specList>
                           <specDesc key="list"/>
                           <specDesc key="item"/>
                           <specDesc key="persName"/>
                           <specDesc key="forename"/>
                           <specDesc key="surname"/>
                           <specDesc key="ref"/>
                           <specDesc key="note"/>
                        </specList>
                     </p>
                     <p><gi>list</gi> with <att>xml:id</att>="bibliography-scholars" groups the
                        information identifying the scholars.</p><!-- Use listPerson instead of just list? -->
                     <p><gi>item</gi> with <att>xml:id</att> and <att>n</att> as <ref
                           target="#bibliography-sigla">described above</ref>.</p>
                     <p><gi>persName</gi> (personal name) groups the information about the scholar's
                        name. Note that it is helpful, but not required, to use <att>ref</att> with
                        the <ref target="https://viaf.org">Virtual International Authorify File
                           (VIAF)</ref> permalink for that person.</p>
                     <p><gi>forename</gi> contains the scholar's first and middle names (middle name
                        optional), or initials, of the scholar.</p>
                     <p><gi>surname</gi> contains the scholar's last name. If the scholars is known
                        by a nickname or shortened name (e.g., Wilamowitz), that information is
                        enclosed in parentheses and quotation marks.</p>
                     <p><gi>ref</gi> (reference) contains a reference to the entry in the
                        bibliography that has citations of the scholar. <att>target</att> with the
                        xml:id of the entry will cause the reference to point to that entry.</p>
                     <p><gi>note</gi> contains further information about the nature of the citation
                        (e.g., "personal correspondence with editor").</p>
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <item xml:id="CSchenkl" n="C. Schenkl">
                           <persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12523146">
                              <forename>Karl</forename>
                              <surname>Schenkl</surname>
                           </persName>
                           <ref target="#Schenkl">H. Schenkl</ref>
                           <note>Unpublished opinions cited in Schenkl's editions.</note>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="Scriverius" n="Scriver.">
                           <persName ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/121894458/">
                              <forename>Pieter</forename>
                              <surname>Schrijver ("Scriverius")</surname>
                           </persName>
                           <ref target="#Burm.">Burman 1731</ref>
                        </item>
                     </egXML>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="edition-text">
            <head>Edition Text</head>
            <p>The edition text corresponds to the text printed "above the line" of the critical
               apparatus in a traditional edition. It is composed of "accepted readings," that is,
               text judged by the editor to be authoritative.</p>
            <p>There may be more than one authoritative version of a text, depending on the text and
               depending on the approach adopted by the editor. Authors sometimes edit and revise
               their work over time. Scribes often record the version of the text that makes sense
               in their context. Scholars and other readers offer conjectures for problematic
               passages. But an editor must make decisions about the text and edition presents to
               readers. The results of those decisions are on display in the official edition
               text.</p>
            <p>Since the online version of an LDLT allows readers to swap readings from the critical
               apparatus into the main text, it is possible to encounter many versions of the text
               in one viewing of it, but the official edition text is the starting point for those
               interactions.</p>
            <p>This section establishes guidelines for encoding the information typically found in
               the main text of a critical edition.</p>
            <div xml:id="edition-text-prose">
               <head>Prose</head>
               <p><!-- Need help here with reference scheme for prose texts.-->
               </p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="edition-text-poetry">
               <head>Verse</head>
               <p>The <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/VE.html"
                     >verse module</ref> of the TEI Guidelines offers many possibilities for marking
                  up various aspects of prosody, but the LDLT is primarily concerned with the <ref
                     target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#COVE">core
                     tags</ref> for encoding the structure of verse texts. This does not mean that
                  editors and others should avoid using the verse module. It means only that the
                  LDLT does not provide functionality for that level of detail.</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="div1"/>
                     <specDesc key="div2"/>
                     <specDesc key="lg"/>
                     <specDesc key="l"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p><gi>div1</gi> (level-1 text division) groups the parts of a book of verse, with
                     <att>type</att>="book" and <att>n</att> with the number of the book.</p>
               <p><gi>div2</gi> (level-2 text division) groups the parts of a single poem (e.g.,
                  stanzas or lines), with <att>type</att>="poem", <att>n</att> with the number of
                  the poem in the book, and <att>met</att> with the name of the meter.</p>
               <!-- Should we require usage of terms from a standard reference work? -->
               <p><gi>lg</gi> (line group) groups one or more verse lines that form a stanza or a
                  couplet, with <att>type</att> and "stanza" or "couplet".</p>
               <!-- Other values?-->
               <p><gi>l</gi> (line) contains the text of a single line of verse, with <att>n</att>
                  and the number of the line.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <div type="book" n="2">
                     <div type="poem" n="1" met="Alcaic Strophe">
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l n="1">Motum ex Metello consule civicum</l>
                           <l n="2">bellique causas et vitia et modos</l>
                           <l n="3">ludumque Fortunae gravisque</l>
                           <l n="4">principum amicitias et arma</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="dialogue">
               <head>Dialogue</head>
               <p>Texts that feature interlocutors (e.g., drama, dialogue) should be encoded using
                     <gi>sp</gi> and <gi>speaker</gi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="sp"/>
                     <specDesc key="speaker"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p><gi>sp</gi> (speech) groups elements related to a person or character's
                  speech.</p>
               <p><att>who</att> is used with <gi>sp</gi> to identify the speaker.</p>
               <p><gi>speaker</gi> contains a human-readable label identifying the person or
                  character speaking the text.</p>
               <p>These features can be used in verse and prose texts:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <sp who="Corydon">
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <l n="1">Nondum Solis equos declinis mitigat aestas,</l>
                     <l n="2">quamvis et madidis incumbant prela racemis</l>
                     <l n="3">et spument rauco ferventia musta susurro.</l>
                     <l n="4">cernis ut ecce pater quas tradidit, Ornyte, vaccae</l>
                     <l n="5">molle sub hirsuta latus explicuere genista?</l>
                     <l n="6">nos quoque vicinis cur non succedimus umbris?</l>
                     <l n="7">torrida cur solo defendimus ora galero?</l>
                  </sp>
               </egXML>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <sp who="Laelius">
                     <speaker>Laelius</speaker>
                     <p>Atqui, Cato, gratissimum nobis, ut etiam pro Scipione pollicear, feceris,
                        si, quoniam speramus, volumus quidem certe, senes fieri, multo ante a te
                        didicerimus quibus facillime rationibus ingravescentem aetatem ferre
                        possimus.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp who="Cato">
                     <speaker>Cato</speaker>
                     <p>Faciam vero, Laeli, praesertim si utrique vestrum, ut dicis, gratum futurum
                        est.</p>
                  </sp>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="people">
               <head>People</head>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="places">
               <head>Places</head>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="edition-text-reference-scheme">
               <head>Reference Scheme</head>

            </div>
            <div xml:id="edition-text-symbols">
               <head>Symbols Commonly Used in the Text of a Critical Edition</head>
               <!-- Sam: do something about telling people who want to do diplomatic stuff to go look at EpiDoc -->
               <p>The symbols in this section have been gleaned from <bibl><author>Martin
                        West</author>, <title>Textual Criticism and Editorial Technique</title>
                        (<pubPlace>Stuttgart</pubPlace>, 1973), <biblScope unit="page"
                        >80–81</biblScope></bibl>.</p>
               <p>For the sake of uniformity, this section follows closely <bibl><author>Tom
                        Elliott</author>, <author>Gabriel Bodard</author>, <author>Elli
                        Mylonas</author>, <author>Simona Stoyanova</author>, <author>Charlotte
                        Tupman</author>, <author>Scott Vanderbilt</author>, et al.
                        <date>(2007-2014)</date>, <title>EpiDoc Guidelines: Ancient documents in TEI
                        XML (Version 8)</title>. Available: <ref
                        target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest"
                        >http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest</ref></bibl>.</p>
               <!-- How should I cite individual sections? By author in the "Responsibility" section of the Epidoc guidelines? -->
               <div xml:id="abbreviation-expansion"
                  corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-abbrevfully.html">
                  <head>Abbreviation Fully Expanded</head>
                  <p>The LDLT follows the Epidoc guidelines for encoding fully expanded
                     abbreviations <ptr
                        target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-abbrevfully.html"/>:</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="expan"/>
                        <specDesc key="abbr"/>
                        <specDesc key="ex"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>expan</gi> (expansion) contains the full expansion of an abbreviation.</p>
                  <p><gi>abbr</gi> (abbreviation) contains the abbreviated part, i.e. the letters
                     actually on the page.</p>
                  <p><gi>ex</gi> (editorial expansion) contains a sequence of letters added by an
                     editor or transcriber when expanding an abbreviation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>a(bc)</quote>
                  </p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <expan>
                        <abbr>a</abbr>
                        <ex>bc</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </egXML>

                  <p>Multiple &lt;abbr&gt; elements within a single &lt;expan&gt; compose a single
                     abbreviation between them. For example, e.g. is one abbreviation for the phrase
                     "exempli gratia."</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <expan>
                        <abbr>e</abbr>
                        <ex>xempli</ex>
                        <abbr>g</abbr>
                        <ex>ratia</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </egXML>
                  <!-- Need discussion of values for @cert on <expan>. Note that different sections in Epidoc guidelines for abbreviations are based on value of @cert  -->
               </div>
               <div xml:id="add-conjecture"
                  corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-restored.html">
                  <head>Text added by emendation</head>
                  <p>An editor supplies text believed to be missing from the original source. (Cf.
                     Epidoc guidelines "Editorial Restoration: Characters Lost But Restored By
                     Modern Editor" <ptr
                        target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-restored.html"/>) </p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="supplied"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>supplied</gi> signifies text believed by the transcriber or editor to be
                     missing.</p>
                  <p><att>reason</att> indicates that text has been omitted, but supplied by
                     emendation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>&lt;abc&gt;</quote>
                  </p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <supplied reason="omitted">abc</supplied>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="undetermined-loss"
                  corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostcharunknown.html">
                  <head>Undetermined Amount Of Text Lost</head>
                  <p>Text has been lost from one or more witnesses. (Cf. Epidoc
                     guidelines, "Lost Characters, Quantity Unknown" <ptr
                        target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostcharunknown.html"
                     />)</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="gap"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>gap</gi> signifies text missing because of damage.</p>
                  <p><att>reason</att> with value "lost" indicates that the text has been lost.</p>
                  <p><att>extent</att> with value "unknown" indicates that an undetermined amount of
                     text has been lost.</p>
                  <p><att>unit</att> with value "characters" indicates that an unspecified number of
                     characters (whether single characters or words or larger groups of text) have
                     been lost.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>[ ]</quote>
                  </p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="character"/>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="known-loss"
                  corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostcharknown.html">
                  <head>Known Amount Of Text Lost</head>
                  <p>The editor or transcriber knows from context and/or observation how much text
                     has been lost. (Cf. Epidoc guidelines, "Lost Characters, Quantity Known" <ptr
                        target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostcharknown.html"
                     />)</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="gap"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>gap</gi> signifies text missing.</p>
                  <p><att>reason</att> with value "lost" indicates that the text has been lost.</p>
                  <p><att>quantity</att> indicates the amount of text has been lost.</p>
                  <p><att>unit</att> indicates the unit measured in <att>quantity</att>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>[ ... ]</quote>
                  </p>
                  <p>Note that each dot represents a missing character.</p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <gap reason="lost" quantity="3" unit="character"/>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="lost-lines-known" corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostlineknown.html">
                  <head>Known Number of Lines Lost</head>
                  <p>A known quantity of lines has been lost, or is conjectured to have been lost
                     from the text of all witnesses. (Cf. Epidoc guidelines, "Lost Lines, Quantity
                     Known" <ptr
                        target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostlineknown.html"
                     />)</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="gap"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>gap</gi> signifies that text is missing.</p>
                  <p><att>reason</att> with value "lost" indicates that the text has been lost.</p>
                  <p><att>quantity</att> indicates the number of lines missing.</p>
                  <p><att>unit</att> with value "line" indicates the unit measured in
                        <att>quantity</att>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>[------]</quote>
                  </p>
                  <p>Note that the brackets and the dashes represent one missing line. The number in
                        <att>quantity</att> will determine the number of instances of that group of
                     characters, one per line.</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <gap reason="lost" quantity="3" unit="line"/>
                  </egXML>
                  <!-- How is this handled differently in prose and verse texts? -->
               </div>
               <div xml:id="lost-lines-unknown" corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostlineunknown.html">
                  <head>Unknown Number of Lines Lost</head>
                  <p>An unknown quantity of lines has been lost, or is conjectured to have been lost
                     from the text of all witnesses. (Cf. Epidoc guidelines, "Lost Lines, Quantity
                     Unknown" <ptr
                        target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-lostlineunknown.html"
                     />)</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="gap"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>gap</gi> signifies that text is missing.</p>
                  <p><att>reason</att> with value "lost" indicates that the text has been lost.</p>
                  <p><att>extent</att> with value "unknown" indicates that nothing more is known about the amount of text that has been lost.</p>
                  <p><att>unit</att> with value "line" indicates the unit measured in
                     <att>extent</att>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>- - - - - -</quote>
                  </p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <gap reason="lost" extent="unknown" unit="line"/>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="editorial-deletion"
                  corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-superfluous.html">
                  <!-- NEED TO EXPLAIN THAT THIS IS WEST'S SUGGESTION AND WE'RE FOLLOWING IT -->
                  <head>Editorial Deletion</head>
                  <p>Text suspected by the editor to be superfluous, but retained in the main text to indicate its traditional attribution to the author. (Cf. Epidoc guidelines, "Superfluous Text" <ptr target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-superfluous.html"/>)</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="surplus"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>surplus</gi> signifies text identified by the editor as added by someone
                     other than the original author.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>{lorem ipsum}</quote>
                  </p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <surplus reason="interpolation">lorem ipsum</surplus>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="crux"
                  corresp="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-ambiguous.html">
                  <!-- Doesn't really correspond to http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-ambiguous.html, but it's close. -->
                  <head>Crux</head>
                  <p>Text deemed by the editor to be irredeemably corrupt. (Cf. Epidoc guidelines, "Ambiguous Characters" <ptr target="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/gl/latest/trans-ambiguous.html"/>)</p>
                  <p>
                     <specList>
                        <specDesc key="unclear"/>
                     </specList>
                  </p>
                  <p><gi>unclear</gi> indicates that the text is readable but not
                     understandable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <quote>†lorem ipsum†</quote>
                  </p>

                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                           <sic>lorem ipsum</sic><!-- How to indicate that this is an editor's determination? -->
                  </egXML>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="apparatus-criticus-patterns">
            <head>Apparatus Criticus</head>
            <p>This section provides models for handling the different kinds of data that occur in
               the apparatus criticus.</p>
            <p>
               <specList>
                  <specDesc key="app"/>
                  <specDesc key="lem"/>
                  <specDesc key="rdg"/>
                  <specDesc key="witDetail"/>
                  <specDesc key="note"/>
               </specList>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="app"><gi>app</gi> (apparatus entry) contains the lemma and readings for a
               single entry in the apparatus criticus, though it and its contents may be nested
               inside of another <gi>app</gi></p>
            <p xml:id="lem"><gi>lem</gi> (lemma) contains a reading judged by the editor to be what
               the author wrote, or as close as possible. This type of reading constitutes the text
               printed in the main portion of a critical edition.</p>
            <p xml:id="rdg"><gi>rdg</gi> (reading) contains some text (or absence of text) witnessed
               by a manuscript or found in an early printed edition where it is not expressly
               proposed, but judged by the editor to be unsatisfactory or corrupt for linguistic
               and/or stylistic reasons. This text is printed in the apparatus criticus.</p>
            <p xml:id="wit"><att>wit</att> (witness) indicates any manuscript(s) or early printed
               edition(s) (esp. without an apparatus or commentary; i.e., <foreign xml:lang="la"
                  >editiones vetustiores</foreign>)</p>
            <p xml:id="source"><att>source</att> (source) indicates any printed edition(s) or other
               scholarly work(s) (e.g., article, textual note, commentary) addressing an aspect of
               the text.</p>
            <p><att>ana</att> (analysis) indicates that a reading belongs to at least one category
               in the LDLT's taxonomy of readings. More than one value is possible.</p>
            <p xml:id="witDetail"><gi>witDetail</gi> (witness detail) contains information about a
               particular witness (<att>wit</att>) to a lemma (<gi>lem</gi>) or reading
                  (<gi>rdg</gi>).</p>
            <p xml:id="note"><gi>note</gi> (note) contains editorial comments, bibliographical
               references, or other information pertaining to the apparatus entry.</p>
            <div>
               <p>Need discussion about the order in which information is presented.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="basic-app-entry">
               <head>Basic reporting of a variant reading</head>
               <p>A <ref target="#wit">witness</ref> or <ref target="#source">source</ref> has a
                  reading that varies from the lemma in some way. For example, if the editor has
                  accepted the text <quote xml:lang="la">Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet</quote> into the
                  main text of the edition, but manuscript <hi rend="bold">A</hi> has <quote
                     xml:lang="la">larem</quote> instead of <quote xml:lang="la">lorem</quote>, the
                  variant reading would be reported in a printed edition as follows:</p>
               <p>
                  <quote>18 larem <hi rend="bold">A</hi></quote>
               </p>
               <p>Since the lemma is not typically printed in an apparatus criticus (unless there is
                  a chance for confusion), it is up to the reader to recognize that <quote
                     xml:lang="la">larem</quote> is a variant for <quote xml:lang="la"
                  >lorem</quote>.</p>
               <p>In this model, an <gi>app</gi> contains both the lemma and the variant reading,
                  reducing the need for guesswork, at least when looking at the XML code.</p>
               <p>The patterns displayed below are designed to handle the various kinds of
                  information conveyed in a typical apparatus criticus, including readings <foreign
                     xml:lang="la">ante correctionem</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="la">in
                     rasura</foreign>, among other paleographical and editorial details.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <p>
                     <app>
                        <lem>Lorem</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#A">larem</rdg>
                     </app> ipsum dolor sit amet </p>
               </egXML>
               <p>If an editor deems it important to indicate that a <gi>rdg</gi> also appears in a
                     <ref target="source"><att>source</att></ref>, the same pattern applies, but
                     <att>source</att> is added after <att>wit</att>:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <p>
                     <app>
                        <lem>Lorem</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#A" source="#Jones">larem</rdg>
                     </app> ipsum dolor sit amet </p>
               </egXML>
               <p>If there are multiple variant readings, another <gi>rdg</gi> should be added for
                  each one.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <p>
                     <app>
                        <lem>Lorem</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#A" source="#Jones">larem</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#B">lurum</rdg>
                     </app> ipsum dolor sit amet </p>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="additions">
               <head>Additions</head>
               <p>A <ref target="#witness">witness</ref> or <ref target="#source">source</ref> adds
                  text (e.g., in the margin) that an editor deems worthy of notice.</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="add"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p><gi>add</gi> (addition) contains text that has been added.</p>
               <p><att>place</att> indicates the placed where the text has been added. Possible
                  values: <list>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">above</hi>: above the line (<hi rend="italic">suprascr. =
                           superscriptum/a</hi>)</item>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">below</hi>: below the line (<hi rend="italic">subscr. =
                           subscriptum/a</hi>)</item>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">bottom</hi>: bottom of the page (<hi rend="italic">ad
                           fin. = ad finem</hi></item>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">inline</hi>: within the body of the original text (<hi
                           rend="italic">in textu</hi>)</item>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">inRas</hi>: in the space where text has been erased. (<hi
                           rend="italic">in ras. = in rasura</hi>)</item>
                     <!-- Note that this is in addition to TEI spec. -->
                     <item><hi rend="bold">margin</hi>: right, left, or both (<hi rend="italic">in
                           mg. = in margine</hi>)</item>
                     <item><hi rend="bold">top</hi>: at the top of the page (<hi rend="italic">ad
                           init. = ad initium</hi></item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p><att>hand</att> indicates the manuscript hand that added the text. See the section
                  on manuscript hands for more information about encoding that information.</p>
               <!-- To be added -->
               <p>For example, the copyist of manuscript <hi rend="bold">N</hi> has the <ref
                     target="#lem">lemma</ref>, but a second hand has added a variant reading in the
                  margin.</p>
               <p>
                  <quote>89 certare] certate <hi rend="bold">G</hi>
                     <hi rend="italic">in mg.</hi></quote>
               </p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem>certare</lem>
                     <rdg wit="#G" xml:id="rdg89certate"><add hand="#G1" place="margin"
                           >certate</add></rdg>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="deletions">
               <head>Deletions</head>
               <p>A <ref target="#witness">witness</ref> or <ref target="#source">source</ref> has
                  deleted some text, and an editor deems it worthy of notice.</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="del"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p><gi>del</gi> (deletion) contains text that has been deleted.</p>
               <p><att>rend</att> (rendition) indicates the method of deletion. Possible values: <list>
                     <item>erasure: text has been physically removed from the page or lines have
                        been drawn through it (<hi rend="italic">del. =
                        delevit/deleverunt</hi>)</item>
                     <item>expunction: text has been marked for deletion with dots underneath (<hi
                           rend="italic">exp. = expunxit/expunxerunt</hi>)</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>For example, the copyist of manuscript <hi rend="bold">N</hi> has printed the <ref
                     target="#lem">lemma</ref>
                  <foreign xml:lang="la">tristique</foreign>, but a later hand has deleted the
                  letters <hi rend="italic">que</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <quote>tristi (que <hi rend="ital">del.</hi>
                     <hi rend="bold">N²</hi>)</quote>
               </p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app ana="#subtractive">
                     <lem>tristique</lem>
                     <rdg wit="#N">tristi<del hand="#N2" rend="erasure">que</del></rdg>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
               <p>Note that <att>ana</att> with value "subtractive" is on the <gi>app</gi> to
                  indicate that the entire entry concerns a reading that takes away something from
                  the lemma. If there are several <gi>rdg</gi> elements and not all of them are
                  subtractive in nature, <att>ana</att> would be applied to the relevant
                     <gi>rdg</gi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="omissions">
               <head>Omissions</head>
               <p>A <ref target="#wit">witness</ref> or <ref target="#source">source</ref> omits
                  some text and the editor deems it important to report the omission.</p>
               <p>For example, the witness known as "P" has omitted the word <foreign xml:lang="la"
                     >pecus</foreign> from the following text: <foreign xml:lang="la">securo custode
                     pecus nocturnaque pastor</foreign>. The traditional apparatus criticus
                  indicates the omission as follows:</p>
               <p>
                  <quote>pecus <hi rend="italic">om.</hi>
                     <hi rend="bold">P</hi></quote>
               </p>
               <p>In this model, the omission is represented by a "self-closing" <gi>rdg</gi>:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <l>securo custode <app ana="#subtractive">
                        <lem>pecus</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#P"/>
                     </app> nocturnaque pastor</l>
               </egXML>
               <p>Note that <att>ana</att> is used with the value "subtractive" to enable querying
                  for this type of data. If there is only one <gi>rdg</gi>, then
                  <att>ana</att>="subtractive" is attached to <gi>app</gi> to indicate that the
                  entire entry in the apparatus concerns an omission. If an omission is to be
                  reported among other readings, <att>ana</att>="subtractive" is applied to the
                     <gi>rdg</gi> that reports the omission:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <l>securo custode <app>
                        <lem>pecus</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#B">pecore</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#P" ana="#subtractive"/>
                     </app> nocturnaque pastor</l>
               </egXML>
               <p>The same model applies to the omission of an entire line of verse, but in that
                  case <gi>app</gi> (with <att>type</att>="lineOmission") and <gi>lem</gi> contain
                  the entire line, and the omission is marked by a self-closing <gi>rdg</gi>:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app type="lineOmission">
                     <lem>
                        <l n="3">et spument rauco ferventia musta susurro.</l>
                     </lem>
                     <rdg wit="#κ #χ"/>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
               <p>This is displayed in the apparatus criticus as <quote><hi rend="italic">vers.
                        om.</hi>
                     <hi rend="italic">κχ</hi></quote></p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="lacuna"
               corresp="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html#TCAPMI">
               <head>Lacuna</head>
               <p>A <ref target="#wit">witness</ref> is missing a portion of the text.</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="lacunaStart"/>
                     <specDesc key="lacunaEnd"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p><gi>lacunaStart</gi> is a self-closing tag with <att>wit</att> indicating where in
                  a witness the lacuna begins.</p>
               <p><gi>lacunaEnd</gi> is a self-closing tag with <att>wit</att> indicating where in a
                  witness the lacuna ends.</p>
               <p>For example, witness <hi rend="bold">N</hi> has a lacuna that begins after the
                  word <foreign xml:lang="la">metus</foreign> and ends before the word <foreign
                     xml:lang="la">arcu</foreign> in the following passage: <quote>Mauris ut mauris
                     et metus pharetra dictum et risus. Suspendisse ut maximus diam. Suspendisse
                     luctus diam non libero pellentesque, et aliquam ex congue. Suspendisse vitae
                     lacinia urna, nec egestas arcu. Quisque eget.</quote></p>
               <p>A traditional apparatus criticus might have the following to indicate the
                  lacuna:</p>
               <p>
                  <quote>pharetra … arcu <hi rend="italic">deest</hi>
                     <hi rend="bold">N</hi></quote>
               </p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <p>Mauris ut mauris et metus <app>
                        <lem>pharetra</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#N"><lacunaStart/></rdg>
                     </app> dictum et risus. Suspendisse ut maximus diam. Suspendisse luctus diam
                     non libero pellentesque, et aliquam ex congue. Suspendisse vitae lacinia urna,
                     nec <app>
                        <lem>egestas</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#N"><lacunaEnd/></rdg>
                     </app> arcu. Quisque eget.</p>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="corrections">
               <head>Corrections</head>
               <p>A variant <ref target="#rdg">reading</ref> has been corrected to the value of the
                     <ref target="#lem">lemma</ref>, but the editor deems the reading prior to
                  correction worthy of notice.</p>
               <p>
                  <specList>
                     <specDesc key="rdgGrp"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <p><gi>rdgGrp</gi> (reading group) contains the readings before and after correction,
                  but since the emphasis is on the original, uncorrected, reading, <att>type</att>
                  is applied with the value "anteCorr" (i.e., <foreign xml:lang="la">ante
                     correctionem</foreign>)</p>
               <p><att>varSeq</att> (variant sequence) indicates the order of the readings (e.g., 1
                  for the first reading, 2 for the correction.</p>
               <p><att>copyOf</att> indicates that the correction is a copy of the <ref
                     target="#lem">lemma</ref>. Instead of copying the value of the lemma, we point
                  to it to indicate that they are the same.</p>
               <p>For example, manuscript <hi rend="bold">N</hi> originally had <foreign
                     xml:lang="la">quaedam</foreign> for the lemma <foreign xml:lang="la"
                     >quidem</foreign>. The editor wishes to note the reading <foreign xml:lang="la"
                     >ante correctionem</foreign>.</p>
               <p>In a traditional critical edition, this would be handled in the apparatus criticus
                  as follows: <quote>quaedam N (ante corr. N¹).</quote> There is no need to print
                  the result of the correction, since "correction" implies the editor's accepted
                  reading (i.e., lemma).</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem xml:id="lem1.33quidem">quidem</lem>
                     <rdgGrp type="anteCorr">
                        <rdg wit="#N" varSeq="1">quaedam</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#N1" varSeq="2" copyOf="#lem1.33quidem"/>
                     </rdgGrp>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
               <p>Note that the <gi>lem</gi> must have an <att>xml:id</att> to be a target for
                     <att>copyOf</att></p>
               <p>This pattern is the basis for a number of other representations of reading
                  sequences.</p>
               <div xml:id="correction-margin">
                  <head>Correction in the Margin</head>
                  <p>A manuscript hand has corrected a variant reading to the lemma by writing it in
                     the margin.</p>
                  <p>For example, manuscript <hi rend="bold">G</hi> has <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >iantabimur</foreign> in the text, but a second hand has added the accepted
                     reading <foreign xml:lang="la">mactabimus</foreign> in the margin. This would
                     be handled in a traditional apparatus as follows: <quote>iantabimur G (corr. G²
                        in mg.)</quote>.</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem4.166mactabimus">mactabimus</lem>
                        <rdgGrp type="anteCorr">
                           <rdg wit="#G" varSeq="1">iantabimur</rdg>
                           <rdg wit="#G" varSeq="2"><add place="margin" copyOf="#lem4.166mactabimus"
                              /></rdg>
                        </rdgGrp>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
                  <p>A self-closing <gi>add</gi> is used here with <att>place</att> and
                        <att>copyOf</att> to indicate that the marginal reading is identical to the
                     accepted reading.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="correction-omission">
                  <head>Correction of an Omission</head>
                  <p>The original copyist has omitted a reading from the text, but another hand (or
                     the original copyist) has supplied the missing text.</p>
                  <p>For example, manuscript <hi rend="bold">G</hi> has omitted the lemma <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">tandem</foreign>, but the original copyist has supplied it. In
                     a traditional critical edition, that would be represented as follows:
                        <quote>tandem] om. G (corr. G¹)</quote>.</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem1.43tandem">tandem</lem>
                        <rdgGrp type="corrOmission">
                           <rdg wit="#G" varSeq="1"/>
                           <rdg wit="#G1" varSeq="2" copyOf="#lem1.43tandem"/>
                        </rdgGrp>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
                  <p>If the corrector has added the reading in the margin or elsewhere (e.g.,
                        <quote>tandem] om. G (corr. G¹ in mg.)</quote>, <gi>add</gi> with
                        <att>place</att> and <att>copyOf</att> can be used:</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app ana="#subtractive">
                        <lem xml:id="lem1.43tandem">tandem</lem>
                        <rdgGrp type="corrOmission">
                           <rdg wit="#G" varSeq="1"/>
                           <rdg wit="#G" varSeq="2"><add place="margin" copyOf="#lem1.43tandem"
                              /></rdg>
                        </rdgGrp>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="correction-addition">
                  <head>Correction by Addition</head>
                  <p>A variant reading differs from the <ref target="lem">lemma</ref> by one or more
                     characters, which have been supplied by the original copyist or another hand at
                     a later time.</p>
                  <p>For example, manuscript <hi rend="bold">N</hi> has <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >insidia</foreign>, which differs from the lemma <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >insidia</foreign>by a single letter "s". A later hand has added the missing
                     "s". That might be handled as follows in a traditional apparatus criticus:
                     insidia N (<hi rend="italic">s</hi> add. N²).</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem3.2insidias">insidias</lem>
                        <rdgGrp type="anteCorr">
                           <rdg wit="#N" varSeq="1">insidia</rdg>
                           <rdg wit="#N2" varSeq="2">insidia<add place="inline">s</add></rdg>
                           <!-- Or should this be handled by a <witDetail>? Or both? -->
                        </rdgGrp>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="correction-deletion">
                  <head>Correction by Deletion</head>
                  <p>A variant reading differs from the <ref target="lem">lemma</ref> by one or more
                     characters, which have been deleted by the original copyist or another hand at
                     a later time.</p>
                  <p>For example, manuscript <hi rend="bold">N</hi> has the reading <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">cogaudete</foreign> where the lemma is just <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">gaudete</foreign>. The original copyist has deleted the
                     letters "co" from the beginning of the word. In a traditional apparatus
                     criticus, that might be printed as follows: <quote>cogaudete <hi rend="bold"
                           >N</hi> (<hi rend="italic">corr.</hi> N¹, co <hi rend="italic"
                        >exp.</hi>)</quote>.</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem2.5gaudete">gaudete</lem>
                        <rdgGrp type="anteCorr">
                           <rdg wit="#N" varSeq="1">cogaudete</rdg>
                           <rdg wit="#N1" varSeq="2" xml:id="rdg2.5gaudete"><del rend="expunction"
                                 >co</del>gaudete</rdg>
                        </rdgGrp>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="correction-with-witDetail">
                  <head>One Witness Among Many Has Been Corrected</head>
                  <p>A variant reading has several witnesses, but only one of them has been
                     corrected, and the editor believes it is important to make that clear.</p>
                  <p>For example, manuscripts <hi rend="bold">P Q R S T U V</hi> have the variant
                     reading <foreign xml:lang="la">flore</foreign> where the lemma is <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">Flora</foreign>. Only manuscript <hi rend="bold">T</hi> has
                     been corrected. In a traditional apparatus criticus, that might be handled as
                     follows: <quote>flore <hi rend="bold">PQRST</hi> (<hi rend="italic">corr.</hi>
                        <hi rend="bold">T¹</hi>) <hi rend="bold">UV</hi></quote>.</p>
                  <p>Since only one witness has been corrected, <gi>rdgGrp</gi> with
                     <att>type</att>="anteCorr" cannot contain the reading of all of the
                     manuscripts, so we must use <att>copyOf</att> on both the lemma and the variant
                     reading.</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem xml:id="lem1.2Flora">Flora</lem>
                        <rdg wit="#P #Q #R #S #U #V" xml:id="rdg1.2">flore</rdg>
                        <rdgGrp>
                           <rdg wit="#T" varSeq="1" copyOf="#rdg1.2flore"/>
                           <rdg wit="#T1" varSeq="2" copyOf="#lem1.2Flora"/>
                        </rdgGrp><!-- Need to consider whether this should be done with <witDetail> instead or in addition to it. -->
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="mutation">
                  <head>Mutation</head>
                  <p>Sometimes the copyist or a later hand "corrects" a variant reading to another
                     variant reading. Although the motivation may have been to correct, the action
                     results in mutation.</p>
                  <p>For example, manuscript <hi rend="bold">N</hi> has <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >dipicta</foreign> for lemma <foreign xml:lang="la">descripta</foreign>, and
                     the original copyist has "corrected" the reading to <foreign xml:lang="la"
                        >depicta</foreign>.</p>
                  <p>A traditional apparatus criticus might handle that as follows: <quote>dipicta
                           <hi rend="bold">N</hi> (<hi rend="italic">mut. in</hi> depicta <hi
                           rend="bold">N¹</hi>)</quote>.</p>
                  <p>The same pattern for the <foreign xml:lang="la">ante correctionem</foreign>
                     scenarios can be used here, with a different value for <att>type</att>
                     ("mutation") on <gi>rdgGrp</gi>:</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <app>
                        <lem wit="#P #V #N2">descripta</lem>
                        <rdgGrp type="mutation">
                           <rdg wit="#N" varSeq="1">dipicta</rdg>
                           <rdg wit="#N1" varSeq="2">depicta</rdg>
                        </rdgGrp>
                     </app>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="conjecture">
               <head>Conjecture</head>
               <p>A conjecture is some portion of text (or absence of text) proposed by some person
                  (ancient or modern) and determined by an editor to be worthy of consideration in
                  establishing the text, but not to be printed in the main text of the edition.</p>
               <p>In a traditional critical edition, a conjecture might be noted as follows:
                     <quote>rapidoque] rabidoque <hi rend="italic">conj.</hi> Baehrens</quote>.</p>
               <p>Although conjectures are more common in modern editions and other scholarship,
                  they are not unheard of in manuscripts, where a hand has written a reading (e.g.,
                  in the margin) that does not resemble any other variant readings and cannot be
                  attributed to a recognizable error. Therefore, conjecture is not limited to those
                  materials identified in <att>source</att>. For this reason, <att>type</att> with
                  value "conjecture" must be used to identify a reading as a conjecture.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app type="conjecture">
                     <lem>rapidoque</lem>
                     <rdg source="#Baehrens">rabidoque</rdg>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
               <p>In this example, <att>type</att> is attached to <gi>app</gi> because the entire
                  entry concerns a conjecture. If the conjecture is just one among many readings,
                     <att>type</att> must be used on the individual <gi>rdg</gi> that contains the
                  conjecture.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem>bullantes</lem>
                     <rdg wit="#ε #δ #e #d2">bullentes</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#η #ν #φ #ρ2 #r #s">bullantis</rdg>
                     <rdg source="#Heins." type="#conjecture">palantes</rdg>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
               <p>If a single scholar has proposed multiple conjectures for a single lemma,
                     <gi>rdgGrp</gi> with <att>type</att> contains all of the conjectures as
                  individual readings:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem>nullos ducet</lem>
                     <rdgGrp type="conjecture">
                        <rdg source="#Heins.">nullosque sui</rdg>
                        <rdg source="#Heins.">nullosque ducis</rdg>
                        <rdg source="#Heins.">nullosque ducum</rdg>
                     </rdgGrp>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
               <p>That should be displayed as: <quote>nullosque sui <hi rend="italic">vel</hi>
                     nullosque duics <hi rend="italic">vel</hi> nullosque ducum <hi rend="italic"
                        >conj.</hi> Heins.</quote></p>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="emendation">
               <head>Emendation</head>
               <p>An emendation is a "successful" <ref target="#conjecture">conjecture</ref>. That
                  is, an emendation is some portion of text (or absence of text) expressly proposed
                  by some person through the application of critical judgment, accepted by the
                  editor in place of the transmitted readings, and printed in the main text of an
                  edition. For this reason, only a <ref target="#lem">lemma</ref> can be classified
                  as an emendation.</p>
               <p>The following example illustrates the difference between an emendation and a
                  conjecture by virtue of the fact that the <gi>lem</gi> has
                  <att>type</att>="emendation" and <gi>rdg</gi> has
                  <att>type</att>="conjecture":</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem source="#Ulit." type="emendation">niteat</lem>
                     <rdg wit="#N #G #β #κ #π #ρ1 #λ1">mutat</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#P #δ" source="#p #t #h #Kempfer #Burm.">mittat</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#μ" ana="#lexical">micat</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#θ #ν #α #η #r #s"
                        source="#o #n #l2 #i2 #Guid. #Wernsd. #Beck #Glaeser #Keene">nutet</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#ε #χ #γ #ρ2 #λ2 #d #e #u #b" source="#i1 #l1 #Tig. #Vienn."
                        >nutat</rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#φ">mutet</rdg>
                     <rdg source="#Leo" type="conjecture">micet ac</rdg>
                     <rdg source="#Barth" type="conjecture">nictat</rdg>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="notes">
               <head>Notes</head>
               <p>An editor wishes to comment on a reading, include bibliographical information, or
                  note something else about the passage in question.</p>
               <p>For example, the editor has recorded a variant reading that another scholar has
                  supported in a textual note. That would be handled in a traditional edition as
                  follows: molle sub] molliter Glaeser, def. Jacoby (Wochenschrift für klassische
                  Philologie III, 1886, p. 1290).</p>
               <p>We handle this with <gi>note</gi> with <att>target</att> pointing at the value of
                     <att>xml:id</att> on the <gi>lem</gi> or <gi>rdg</gi> in question.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app>
                     <lem wit="#P #V" source="#edd.">molle sub</lem>
                     <rdg wit="#N #G #A #H" source="#Glaeser #Keene" xml:id="rdg1.5molliter"
                        >molliter</rdg>
                     <rdg source="#Schenkl2">molle per</rdg>
                     <note target="#rdg1.5molliter"><ref target="#Jacoby">Jacoby</ref> defendit
                           (<ref
                           target="https://books.google.de/books?id=q5blAAAAMAAJ&amp;hl=de&amp;pg=PA128#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false"
                           >Wochenschrift für klassische Philologie</ref> III, 1886, p. 1290)</note>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
